Guide to the Lola Gornall Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lola Gornall papers
1883-1945
WA MSS S-2715
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
6.5
(7 boxes)
The collection contains correspondence, drafts of writings, clippings, photographs, and printed material documenting the life and work of Australian writer Lola Gornall, and in particular her relationship with the American writer Zane Grey. The bulk of the collection consists of extensive correspondence from Grey between 1933 and 1938, and includes some letters written in a private code (a key created by the dealer is present). Drafts of Gornall's writings include three collections of verse for children, including "Sing a Song of Sydney" and "New Zealand Nursery Rhymes," as well as a group of poems titled "King's Cross Nights". The collection also includes correspondence from others, clippings documenting Gornall's career, a family Bible, and books inscribed to her by Zane Grey and other writers. Zane Grey's engagement calendar for 1935 is also present.
Gornall, Lola, 1884-1969
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Serendipity Books on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2002.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Lola Gornall (1884-1969)
The writer Lola Sydney Gornall was born in Sydney, Australia, on January 24, 1884, to Peter and Alice Hardman Gornall, proprietors of The Suburban Times, Redfern, Sydney. She had one sister, Olive Agnes Gornall Clough. Lola Gornall was a poet and a drama critic, and a member of the Australian Journalists Association. Her poems were published in a variety of periodicals and anthologies, chiefly in Australia and New Zealand, in the early twentieth century.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains correspondence, drafts of writings, clippings, photographs, and printed material documenting the life and work of Australian writer Lola Gornall, and in particular her relationship with the American writer Zane Grey. The bulk of the collection consists of extensive correspondence from Grey between 1933 and 1938, and includes some letters written in a private code. Drafts of Gornall's writings include three collections of verse for children, including "Sing a Song of Sydney" and "New Zealand Nursery Rhymes," as well as a group of poems titled "King's Cross Nights". The collection also includes correspondence from others, clippings documenting Gornall's career, a family bible, and books inscribed to her by Zane Grey and other writers. Zane Grey's engagement calendar for 1935 is also present.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Zane Grey correspondence, 1933-1938. II. Writings, 1923-circa 1945. III. Other papers, 1883-1939.
Authors, American -- 20th Century; Authors, Australian -- 20th Century -- Archives; Ciphers (codes); Photographic prints; Authors; Gornall, Lola, 1884-1969; Grey, Zane, 1872-1939
- Zane Grey correspondence, 1933-1938; Series I; 5.42; (6 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Arranged roughly chronologically by year.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I contains letters from Zane Grey to Lola Gornall, many of them enclosing photographs and annotated clippings; a few enclose dried plants. Many of the letters are written partially or entirely in code. A copy of a key to this code created by the dealer is filed at the end of the undated correspondence.
  - 1933-1934, 30 (Box 1)
  - 1934-1935, 33 (Box 2)
  - 1935-1936, 29 (Box 3)
  - 1937-1938, undated, 28 (Box 4)
  - Undated, 31 (Box 5)
  - Undated, 13 (Box 6)
- Writings, 1923-circa 1945; Series II; 0.5
  Series II consists chiefly of drafts of poems by Lola Gornall, but also includes some published versions of individual poems as well as correspondence and clippings documenting her career.
  - "King's Cross Nights", draft, typescript, undated (Box 7)
  - "New Zealand Nursury Rhymes", draft, typescript, undated (Box 7)
  - "Sing a Song of Sydney", specimen copy, undated (Box 7)
  - Untitled, "To every child -- everywhere", draft, typescript, undated (Box 7)
  - Poems, drafts, typescript, undated (Box 7)
  - Poems, published versions clipped from periodicals, undated (Box 7)
  - Correspondence and clippings, 1923-circa 1945; 2 (Box 7)
- Other Papers, 1883-1944; Series III; 0.5
  The series contains photographs, clippings and ephemera, much of it likely sent to Gornall by Zane Grey; Zane Grey's 1935 engagement calendar; inscribed books; and the Gornall family bible, which includes genealogical information.
  - Photograph of Lola Gornall (Box 7)
  - Photographs of Zane Grey (Box 7)
  - Zane Grey "Ready Reference Dairy", 1935 (Box 7)
  - Clippings and ephemera, 3 (Box 7)
  - Books inscribed to Gornall from Grey and others, 1923-1944; 8 (Box 7)
    Includes one book inscribed to Gornall's nephew, the poet Maurice Clough.
  - Gornall family bible, 1883-1939; 2 (Box 7)